\mathbf{H} PPY $\mathbf{B}\mathbf{U}\mathbf{Z}$ \mathbf{B}

Postdoctoral Researcher Princeton University Email:hbuzaaba@gmail.com

RESEARCH INTEREST

My current research focuses on developing technologies for African languages. In the past, I spent time investigating the use of natural-gradient Bayesian methods to improve uncertainty estimation in pre-trained language models and how to make them robust and adaptable with a keen interest in low resource African languages.

EMPLOYMENT

Postdoctoral Research Associate

Princeton University

Postdoctoral Researcher, Approximate Bayesian Inference Team

RIKEN Center for Advanced Intelligence Project

Ph.D Student, Systems and Information Engineering

University of Tsukuba

From September 2023

Princeton NJ. USA

From June 2022 - August 2023

Tokyo, Japan

April 2018 - March 2022

Tsukuba, Japan

EDUCATION

Ph.D Computer Science, University of Tsukuba

Supervisor: Prof. Toshiyuki Amagasa.

Master of Regional Development, Toyo University

Supervisor: Prof. Nakabasami Chieko.

Bachelor of Applied Physics, UR College of Science and Technology (Former KIST)

Thesis Supervisor: Prof. Pogrebnoi Alexander.

April 2018 - March 2022

Sept 2015 - Sept 2017

Jan 2008 - Mar 2012

LIST OF PUBLICATIONS

- O. Ogundepo, T. Gwadabe, C. Rivera, J. Clark, S. Ruder, D. Adelani, B. Dossou, A. DIOP, C. Sikasote, G. Hacheme, H. Buzaaba, I. Ezeani, R. Mabuya, S. Osei, C. Emezue, A. Kahira, S. Muhammad, A. Oladipo, A. Owodunni, A. Tonja, I. Shode, A. Asai, T. Ajayi, C. Siro, S. Arthur, M. Adeyemi, O. Ahia, A. Anuoluwapo, O. Awosan, C. Chukwuneke, B. Opoku, A. Ayodele, V. Otiende, C. Mwase, B. Sinkala, A. Rubungo, D. Ajisafe, E. Onwuegbuzia, H. Mbow, E. Niyomutabazi, E. Mukonde, F. Lawan, I. Ahmad, J. Alabi, M. Namukombo, M. Chinedu, M. Phiri, N. Putini, N. Mngoma, P. Amuok, R. Iro, S. Adhiambo. AfriQA: Cross-lingual Open-Retrieval Question Answering for African Languages. In the International Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing EMNLP2023).
- 2. C. Bamba, D. Adelani, P. Nabende, J. Alabi, T. Sindane, H. Buzaaba, S. Muhammad, C. Emezue, P. Ogayo, A. Aremu, C. Gitau, D. Mbaye, J. Mukiibi, B. Sibanda, B. F. P. Dossou, A. Bukula, R. Mabuya, A. Tapo, E. Munkoh-Buabeng, V. Koagne, F. Kabore, A. Taylor, G. Kalipe, T. Macucwa, V. Marivate, T. Gwadabe, E. Mboning, I. Onyenwe, G. Atindogbe, T. Adelani, I. Akinade, O. Samuel, M. Nahimana, T. Musabeyezu, E. Niyomutabazi, E. Chimhenga, K. Gotosa, P. Mizha, A. Agbolo, S. Traore, C. Uchechukwu, A. M. Abdullahi, D. Klakow. MasakhaPOS: Part-of-Speech Tagging for Typologically Diverse African languages. In the 61st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics ACL2023).
- 3. T. Adewumi, M. Adeyemi, A. Anuoluwapo, B. Peters, **H. Buzaaba**, O. Samuel, A. M. Rufai, B. Ajibade, T. Gwadabe, M. K. Traore, T. Ajayi, S. Muhammad, A. Baruwa, P. Owoicho, T. Ogunremi, P. Ngigi, O. Ahia, R. Nasir, F. Liwicki, M. Liwicki. AfriWOZ: Corpus for Exploiting Cross-Lingual Transferability for Generation of Dialogues in Low-Resource, African Languages. *In the International Joint Conference on Neural Networks IJCNN 2023*).
- 4. D. Adelani, G. Neubig, S. Ruder, S. Rijhwani, M. Beukman, C. Palen-Michel, C. Lignos, J. Alabi, S. Muhammad, P. Nabende, C. M. B. Dione, A. Bukula, R. Mabuya, B. F. P. Dossou, B. Sibanda, **H. Buzaaba**, J. Mukiibi,

- G. Kalipe, D. Mbaye, A. Taylor, F. Kabore, C. C. Emezue, A. Aremu, P. Ogayo, C. Gitau, E. Munkoh-Buabeng, V. M. Koagne, A. A. Tapo, T. Macucwa, V. Marivate, M. T. Elvis, T. Gwadabe, T. Adewumi, O. Ahia, J. Nakatumba-Nabende, N. L. Mokono, I. Ezeani, C. Chukwuneke, M. O. Adeyemi, G. Q. Hacheme, I. Abdulmumin, O. Ogundepo, O. Yousuf, T. Moteu, D. Klakow. MasakhaNER 2.0: Africa-centric Transfer Learning for Named Entity Recognition. In Proceedings of the 2022 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing, EMNLP), 2022.
- 5. D. Adelani, J. Alabi, A. Fan, J. Kreutzer, X. Shen, M. Reid, D. Ruiter, D. Klakow, P. Nabende, E. Chang, T. Gwadabe, F. Sackey, B. F. P. Dossou, C. Emezue, C. Leong, M. Beukman, S. Muhammad, G. Jarso, O. Yousuf, A. N. Rubungo, G. Hacheme, E. P. Wairagala, M. U. Nasir, B. Ajibade, T. Ajayi, Y. Gitau, J. Abbott, M. Ahmed, M. Ochieng, A. Aremu, P. Ogayo, J. Mukiibi, F. O. Kabore, G. Kalipe, D. Mbaye, A. A. Tapo, V. M. Koagne, E. Munkoh-Buabeng, V. Wagner, I. Abdulmumin, A. Awokoya, H. Buzaaba, B. Sibanda, A. Bukula, S. Manthalu. A Few Thousand Translations Go a Long Way! Leveraging Pre-trained Models for African News Translation. In Proceedings of the 2022 Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics NAACL), 2022.
- 6. **H. Buzaaba**, T. Amagasa. A scheme for efficient question answering with low dimension reconstructed embeddings. In The 23rd international conference on information integration and web intelligence iiWAS) 2021.
- D. I. Adelani, J. Abbott, G. Neubig, D. D'souza, J. Kreutzer, C. Lignos, C. Palen-Michel, H. Buzaaba, S. Rijhwani, S. Ruder, S. Mayhew, I. A. Azime, S. H. Muhammad, C. C. Emezue, J. Nakatumba-Nabende, P. Ogayo, A. Anuoluwapo, C. Gitau, D. Mbaye, J. Alabi, S. M. Yimam, T. R. Gwadabe, I. Ezeani, R. A. Niyongabo, J. Mukiibi, V. Otiende, I. Orife, D. David, S. Ngom, T. Adewumi, P. Rayson, M. Adeyemi, G. Muriuki, E. Anebi, C. Chukwuneke, N. Odu, E. P. Wairagala, S. Oyerinde, C. Siro, T. S. Bateesa, T. Oloyede, Y. Wambui, V. Akinode, D. Nabagereka, M. Katusiime, A. Awokoya, M. MBOUP, D. Gebreyohannes, H. Tilaye, K. Nwaike, D. Wolde, A. Faye, B. Sibanda, O. Ahia, B. F. P. Dossou, K. Ogueji, T. I. DIOP, A. Diallo, A. Akinfaderin, T. Marengereke, S. Osei. MasakhaNER: Named Entity Recognition for African Languages. Transactions of the Association for Computational Linguistics 2021) 9: 1116–1131.
- 8. **H. Buzaaba**, T. Amagasa. Question Answering Over Knowledge Base: A Scheme for Integrating Subject and the Identi ed Relation to Answer Simple Questions. SN COMPUT. SCI. 2, 25 2021).
- 9. **H. Buzaaba**, T. Amagasa. A modular approach for efficient simple question answering over knowledge base. In the 30th international conference on Database and expert systems applications DEXA), 2019.

TEACHING

Data Engineering 1 for master's students Teaching Assistant University of Tsukuba	Oct – Dec 2019 Tsukuba, Japan
Database systems for undergraduate students Teaching Assistant University of Tsukuba	Oct – Dec 2018 Tsukuba, Japan

REVIEWING

2024	LREC
2023	NeurIPS
2022	NeurIPS, ACML

2022 Neurin 5, 1

2021 ICLR

OTHER ACTIVITIES

2024 Co-organizing the ICLR2023 workshop on AfricaNLP.2023 Co-organizing the ICLR2023 workshop on AfricaNLP.

PRIZES AWARDS

- 1. 2019: **Merit Award**, Students award for best presenter at the 11th Forum on Data Engineering and Information Management DEIM 2019.
- 2. 2017: Mastuo Award, an award for best master thesis of Regional Development Studies, by Toyo University.
- 3. 2015: **Abe-Initiative Scholarship**, a fully funded masters scholarship awarded to young Africans by the Japanese government.